Inventory of the Rockwell Hereford papers, 1850-1977
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Rockwell Hereford papers
1850-1977
1953-1963
Hereford, Rockwell, 1902-1988
06175
6 cubic ft. (9 document boxes, 2 slim document boxes, 1 F24D box)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Manuscript, photographs, illustrations, and extensive research materials by this division of U.S. Steel Corporation’s manager of employee publications for a pamphlet series on the history of western industry entitled, 100 Years West of the Hundredth Meridian (or 100 Years West of 100º).
Biography of Rockwell Hereford
Author Rockwell Hereford was born April 12, 1902 to Adeline Lucina (Rockwell) and Frank H. Hereford (distinguished Tucson, Arizona attorney). He married Marda Leppo and had three children, David, Frances, and Anne.
While employed with Consolidated Western Steel, a division of United States Steel Corporation, Hereford wrote a series of pamphlets on the history of western industry entitled 100 Years West of the Hundredth Meridian. Later, he was transferred to U.S. Steel’s Columbia-Geneva Steel Division as manager of employee publications. His charge was to inaugurate an employee communication program involving a monthly magazine, U.S.S. Westerners. This magazine, started in November 1956, was published for employees and families of Columbia-Geneva Steel and Columbia Iron Mining Company. The “100 Years West” series was planned to continue, but was cut due to budget constraints.
A biographer of Henry M. Robinson, who was a banker and fiscal policy advisor to Herbert Hoover, Hereford authored the book, A Whole Man, Henry Mauris Robinson, and a Half Century, 1890-1940. (The manuscript and research materials for this book are housed at the Hoover Presidential Library in Iowa.)
Rockwell Hereford died November 26, 1988.
Scope and Content
The Rockwell Hereford papers contain the manuscripts, photographs, illustrations, and extensive research materials for a pamphlet series on the history of western industry entitled, 100 Years West of the Hundredth Meridian (or 100 Years West of 100º). The series was planned to commemorate 100 years of experience in the fabrication of iron and steel products for all industries of the West.
The research files include notes and anecdotes taken from a variety of secondary sources. (Note that 19th century research materials and illustrations are reproductions, or notes taken from books with 19th century copyright dates.) Topics researched include the history of the West, mining, transportation, communication, lumber and pulp, agriculture, petroleum and natural gas, iron and steel, water resources, food processing, chemicals, fabricated metals, machinery, construction, the economy of the West, and an overview of U.S. Steel’s contribution to western industry. A large number of photographs and illustrations accompany each of these topics, including a set of postcards depicting paintings of the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad and the industries it served by railroad artist Howard Fogg.
There is also a complete set of Columbia-Geneva Steel Division’s employee publication U.S.S. Westerners, November 1956-December 1963, with an index to all volumes.
The biographical file contains a typewritten portrait of Adeline Lucina Rockwell Hereford, Rockwell Hereford’s mother. The information, recorded by Rockwell’s wife, Marda, was provided by several close friends of Adeline.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There is one other known archival collection created by Rockwell Hereford as of the date of processing. See:
Rockwell Hereford Collection, The Herbert Hoover Presidential Library-Museum, P.O. Box 488, 210 Parkside Drive, West Branch, IA 52358
Acquisition Information
Anne Hereford Rohrbach donated her father’s papers to the American Heritage Center in March 1989.
Access Terms
Hereford, Adeline Lucina Rockwell.;; Industries--West (U.S.);;; Manuscripts.; Photographs.;; U.S.S. Westerners.; Hereford, Marda.; United States Steel Corporation.
Business, Industry, Labor, and Commerce; Businesses and Corporations
Container List
- Biographical, Series I.
  - Hereford Family History, 1974, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- United States Steel Corporation, Series II.
  - 100 Years West of 100º, Sub-series 1.
    - Manuscript:
      - Contents, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Historical Background: Turning Back the Calendar, The West Prior to 1854, and 1854 in the West, April 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Industries:
        - Agriculture and Fishery, August 1954-May 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Chemicals, November 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Communication, February-March 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Construction, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Fabricated Metals, December 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Food Processing, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - Iron and Steel, September 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Lumber and Pulp, May 1954-November 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - Machinery, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - Mining, June, November 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - Other Industries and Trade, December 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - Petroleum and Natural Gas, February-August 1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Transportation, April 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Transportation Equipment, November 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - Water Resources, April, August 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Introduction: A Brief History of the Development of Western Industry, November 1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - U.S. Steel in the West, March 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Photographs and Illustrations:
      - Agriculture and Fishery, 1891-circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Chemicals, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Communication, 1850-1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Construction, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Fabricated Metals, 1926-1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Food Processing, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Historical Background, 1852-circa 1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Iron and Steel, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Lumber and Pulp, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Machinery:
        - Agricultural, 1860-1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - Mining, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
        - Other, 1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Mining, 1876-circa 1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Other Industries and Trades, 1880, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Petroleum and Natural Gas, 1898-1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Transportation:
        - Other, 1856-1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - Railroad, 1867-1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Transportation Equipment, 1875-1946 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - U.S. Steel in the West:
        - Columbia Iron Mining Co., Iron Mountain, Utah, August 1935 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        - The Consolidated Western Steel Story, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
        - General, 1870-1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Water Resources, 1885-1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Planning, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Research Files:
      - Agriculture and Fishery, 1893-1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Banking and Finance, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Bibliography, undated (Box 4, Folders 3-4)
      - Chemicals, 1948-1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Communication, 1907-1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Economy of the West, 1930-1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 1854 in the West, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Fabricated Metals, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Food Processing, 1926-1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Iron and Steel, 1926-1953 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Lumber and Pulp, 1916-1954 (Box 5, Folders 1-2)
      - Machinery, 1883-1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Mining, 1888-1954 (Box 5, Folders 4-5)
      - Miscellaneous, circa 1953 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Other Industries and Trades, 1895-1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Petroleum and Natural Gas:
        - General (Box 5, Folder 8)
        - General (Box 6, Folders 1-2)
        - Pipelines (Transmission), 1948-1955 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Printing and Publishing, 1934-1952 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Recreation and Tourism, 1938-1955 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Schools and Education, 1907-1950 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Transportation:
        - Other, 1868-1954 (Box 6, Folders 7-9)
        - Railroad: Building the Rock Island Railroad by Arthur W. Lange, April 1953 (Box 6, Folder 10)
        - Railroad: General, 1867-1955 (Box 6, Folder 11)
        - Railroad: General, 1867-1955 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Transportation Equipment, 1880-1960 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Turning Back the Calendar:
        - General, 1939-1954 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - States’ Chronologies, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - U.S. Steel in the West:
        - Consolidated Steel Corporation: Summary of Facilities, Operating Results, Financial Condition and Pertinent Information, June 1948 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - General, 1936-1958 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        - Report by Alden G. Roach on Consolidated Western Steel Corporation, January 1949 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        - Twenty Years of Consolidated Steel Corporation: 1928-1948, January 1949 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        - Western Pipe and Steel Company of California, circa 1929 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Water Resources, 1895-1954 (Box 8, Folders 2-4)
      - The West Prior to 1854, 1931-1954 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Other Projects, Sub-series 2.
    - Miscellaneous, 1911, 1929, 1961-1968 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Pamphlets, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Photographs:
      - American Steel & Wire Co., Pacific Works, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Columbia-Geneva Steel, 1956-1963 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Columbia Steel Corporation:
        - Columbia Coal Mine, Utah, circa 1910-1924 (Box 8, Folder 10)
        - Employees, 1937-1947 (Box 8, Folder 11)
        - Pittsburg, California Plant, 1923-1937 (Box 8, Folder 12)
        - Provo, Utah Plant Site, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 13)
        - Wire and Wire Rope Co., circa 1935 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Postcards, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
      (Depicting series of paintings by Howard Fogg of the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad and the industries it served)
    - Press Kit: Design in Steel, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - U.S.S. Westerners, Sub-series 3.
    - Atlantic City (Wyoming) Project: Research File, 1960-1961 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - I Remember When…, September/October 1963 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Photographs:
      - Blohm, R.H. (Cap), 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Blough, Roger M., 1958 (Box 9, Folder 7)
        (Chairman & C.E.O., U.S. Steel Corp.)
      - Cranfill, Harvey C., 1959-1963 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous Mines, Plants, and Equipment, 1955-1963 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Purvance, W. Truxton (Box 9, Folder 10)
        (Project Engineer, U.S. Steel Corp.)
      - Roach, Alden G., 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 11)
        (President, Columbia-Geneva Steel Division, U.S. Steel)
      - U.S. Steel Personnel, 1953-1962 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Utah, circa 1940-1960 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Worthington, Leslie B., 1957-1960 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - U.S.S. Westerners:
      - Index (to all volumes), November 1956-December 1963 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Vol. 1, No. 1 – Vol. 2, No. 11, November 1956-December 1957 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Vol. 3. Nos. 1-10, January-December 1958 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Vol. 4, No. 1 – Vol. 5, No. 10, January 1959-December 1960 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Vol. 6, Nos. 1-9, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Vol. 7, No. 1 – Vol. 8, No. 6, January 1962-November/December 1963 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Oversized Materials, Series III.
  - Biographical: Guest Book, 1911-1921 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 100 Years West of 100º:
    - Manuscript: Illustrations Used, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      (Includes “Western Agriculture” Map)
    - Photographs and Illustrations, 1852-circa 1954 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Research Files, 1867-1954 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Other Projects:
    - Graphics, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Photo Album: Columbia Steel Company, Steel Foundry Plant, Pittsburg, California, 1910 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Photo Album: Columbia Steel Company, Pittsburg, California, 1920-1922 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Photo Album: Columbia Steel Corporation, Columbia Plant, Utah, 1923-1924 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, circa 1900-circa 1930 (Box 12, Folder 9)